[Music]
Reedman
reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
[Music]
9 Now, for the first time in his 12 years of life, Jonas felt separate,
different. He remembered what the Chief had said: that his training would be alone and
apart. But his training had not yet begun and already, upon leaving the Auditorium, he felt the
apartness. Holding the folder she had given him made his way through the
throng, looking for his family unit and for Asher. People moved aside for him.
They watched him. He thought he could hear whispers. "Ash!" he called, spotting his
friend near the rows of bicycles.
"Ride back with me?" "Sure." Asher smiled, his usual smile,
friendly and familiar. But Jonas felt a moment of hesitation from his friend and
uncertainty. "Congratulations," Asher said.
"You too," Jonas replied. "It was really funny, when she told about the smacks. You
got more applause than almost anybody else." The other new TW clustered nearby,
placing their folders carefully into the carrying containers on the back backs of
the bikes. In each dwelling tonight they would be studying the instructions for
the beginning of their training. Each night for years the children had memorized the required
lessons for school, often yawning with boredom. Tonight they would all begin
eagerly to memorize the rules for their adult Assignments. "Congratulations, Asher!"
someone called. Then that hesitation again. "You too, Jonas!" Asher and Jonas
responded with congratulations to their groupmates. Jonas saw his parents
watching him from the place where their own bicycles were
waiting. Lily had already been strapped into her seat. He waved. They waved back, smiling,
but he noticed that Lily was watching him solemnly, her thumb and her mouth. He
rode directly to his dwelling, exchanging only small jokes and unimportant remarks
with Asher. "See you in the morning, Recreation Director!" he called,
dismounting by his door as Asher continued on. "Right! See you!" Asher called
back. Once again, there was just a moment when things weren't quite the same,
weren't quite as they had always been through the long friendship. Perhaps he had imagined it.
Things couldn't change, with Asher. The evening meal was quieter than
usual. Lily chattered about her plans for volunteer work; she would begin, she said,
at the Nurturing Center, since she she was already an expert at feeding Gabriel.
"I know," she added quickly, when her father gave her a warning glance, "I won't
mention his name. I know I'm not supposed to know his name. "I can't wait for
tomorrow to come," she said happily Jonah sighed uneasily. "I can," he
muttered. "You've been greatly honored," his mother said. "Your father and I are very
proud." "It's the most important job in the community," Father
said. "But just the other night, you said the job of making Assignments was the most
important!" Mother nodded. "This is different. It's not a job, really. I never
thought, never expected—" She paused. "There's only one Receiver." "But the
Chief Elder said that they had made a selection before, and that it failed. What was she talking
about?" Both of his parents hesitated. Finally his father described the previous
selection. "It was very much as it was today, Jonas— —the same suspense, as 111 had
been passed over when the Assignments were given. Then the announcement, when
they singled out the one—" Jonas interrupted. "What was his name?" His mother
replied, "Her, not his. It was a female. But we are never to speak the
name, or to use it again for a new child Jonas was shocked.
A name designated not to be spoken indicated the highest degree of disgrace.
"What happened to her?" he asked nervously.
But his parents looked blank. "We don't know," his father said uncomfortably. "We never saw her
again." A silence fell over the room. They looked at each other. Finally his mother,
rising from the table, said, "You've been greatly honored, Jonas. Greatly honored."
Alone in his sleeping room prepared for bed, Jonas opened his folder at
last. Some of the other Twelves, he had noticed been given folders thick with printed
pages. He imagined Benjamin, the scientific male in his group, beginning
to read pages of rules and instructions with relish pictured Fiona smiling her gentle
smile as she bent over the lists of duties and methods that she would be
required to learn in the days to come.
But his own folder was startlingly close to empty. Inside there was only a single
printed sheet. He read it
twice. JONAS RECEIVER OF MEMORY number one Go immediately at the
end of school hours each day to the Annex entrance behind the House of the
Old and present yourself to the attendant number two Go immediately to
your dwelling at the conclusion of Training Hours each day number three
in this moment you are exempted from rules governing rudess You may ask any
question of any citizen and you will receive answers number four Do not discuss your
training with any other member of the community, including parents and
Elders number five in this moment you are prohibited from dreamt telling
number six Except for illness or injury unrelated to your training, do not apply for any
medication number seven You are not permitted to apply for release number eight You may
lie. Jonas was stunned. What would happened to his friendships? His mindless hours playing
ball, or riding his bike along the river?
Those have been happy in vital times for him. Were they to be completely taken
from him, now simple logis instructions— —where to go, and when— —were
expected. Every 12 had to be told, of course, where and how and when to report for
training he was a little dismayed that his schedule left no time, apparently, for
recreation. The exemption from rudess startled him. Reading it again, however, he
realized that it didn't compel him to be rude simply allowed him the
option. He was quite certain he would never take advantage of it.
He was so completely, so thoroughly accustomed to courtesy within the
community that the thought of asking another citizen an intimate question, of
calling someone's attention to an area of awkwardness, was unnerving. The prohibition of dreamt
telling he thought, would not be a real problem. He dreamed so rarely that the
dreamt telling did not come easily to him anyway he was glad to be excused
from it. He wondered briefly, though, how to deal with it at the morning
meal. What if he did dream— —should he simply tell his family unit, as he did so
often, anyway, that he hadn't? That would be a lie. Still, the
final rule said while he wasn't quite ready to think about the final rule on the
page. The restriction of medication unnerved him. Medication was always
available to citizens, even to children, through their parents. When he had crushed his finger
in the door had quickly, gasping into the speaker, notified his mother; she had
hastily requisitioned relief of pain medication which had promptly been delivered to his
dwelling. Almost instantly the excruciating pain in his hand had
diminished to the throb which was, now, all he could recall of the
experience rereading rule number six he realized that a crushed finger fell into
the category of "unrelated training." So if it ever happened again—
—and he was quite certain it wouldn't; he had been very careful near heavy
doors since the accident!— !—he could still receive medication. The pill he took now, each
morning, was also unrelated to training.
So he would continue to receive the pill he remembered uneasily what the
Chief Elder had said about the pain that would come with his training. She had called it
indescribable. Jonas swallowed hard, trying without success to imagine what
such pain might be like was no medication at all. But it was beyond his
comprehension. He felt no reaction to rule number seven at all. It had never
occurred to him that under any circumstances, ever, he might apply for
release. Finally he stealed himself to read the final rule
again. He had been trained since earliest childhood, since his earliest learning of
language, never to lie. It was was an integral part of the learning of precise
speech. Once, when he had been a Four, he had said, just prior to the midday meal at
school, "I'm starving." Immediately he had been taken aside for a brief private
lesson in language precision. He was not starving, it was
pointed out. He was hungry. No one in the community was starving, had ever been
starving, would ever be starving. To say "starving" was to speak a lie and An
unintentional lie, of course. But the reason for precision of language was to
ensure that unintentional lies were never uttered. Did you understand that?
they asked him. And he had. He had never, within his memory, been
tempted to lie. Asher did not lie. Lily did not lie. His parents did not lie. No
one did.
Unless... Now Jonas had a thought that he had never had before. This new thought
was frightening.
What if others— —adults —had, upon becoming Twelves, received in their instructions the same
terrifying sentence? What if they had all been instructed: You may lie? His mind
Reed Now, empowered to ask questions of utmost rudeness— —and promised answers— —he
could, conceivably (though it was almost unimaginable), ask someone, some adult, his
father perhaps: "Do you lie?" But he would have no way of knowing
if the answer he received were true
[Music]